Do we all agree that soda is not a
benefit for our health? I think across
the nutrition aisle, we can shake hands
in agreement over that statement, but
it's recently been discovered exactly
how cancer spreads more aggressively
across the body when we consume soda or
pop as you Midwesterners will correct
me. In a fascinating study, when an
enzyme is removed from the body, animals
with cancer experience a massive
stoppage to cancer metastasis. That's
the spreading of cancer to other regions
of the body. And don't worry, we're
going to go over human research, too.
That enzyme is called sword, and it's
the lynch pin between cancer and soda.
Let me explain. The two most well-known
nutrients in soda are glucose and
fructose. So, those are two sugars. Have
you ever heard of high fructose corn
syrup? That's the glucose and slightly
more fructose. And it's used heavily in
soda. So when we expose a variety of
colorctyl cancer cells to either glucose
that's found in our bloodstream or the
combination of glucose plus fructose
what we deliver to our bloodstream
through soda consumption we see some
striking results. The orange is our
troublemaker condition. The combination
with fructose and we're looking at four
different colorctyl cancer cell lines.
The higher the bars go, the more
aggressive the cancer cells are, meaning
the greater metastasis potential. We can
even see that in the microscope images
on the right. The more color you see,
the more cancer cells have invaded.
Clearly, the combination leads to more
aggression. Okay, great. But what does
that have to do with sword? Well, when
we probe tumors and measure the amount
of sword expression, meaning the more of
the sore gene is read by the cell and
produced into a functional protein, we
see a significant rise in sword
expression compared to non-cancerous
tissue. So that means that there's at
least an association between sword and
cancer. But that doesn't tell us the
relationship to soda yet. At this point,
we know two things. One, fructose
combined with glucose like in soda makes
colurectal cancer more aggressive. Two,
cancerous tumors contain a lot more of
this sword gene expression than normal
tissues. Now, if we return to what I
said earlier, this enzyme sword and when
it's knocked out or removed from the
body, cancer doesn't spread nearly at
the same level as when it's present in
cancer. We can see that here. The higher
the bars, the more cancer is spread. Not
a good thing. The WT there are mice with
the sword gene intact and the KO are
knockout there. So are mice with sword
exised from their cancer cells. Now
cancer metastasis is clearly massively
diminished. And equally poignantly in
the images to the right, the hot spots,
the color are that you're seeing there
are mice that have tagged cancer cells.
It's clear that there are far more hot
spots, i.e. cancer cells in the sword
intact mice. Okay, sword is important.
Got it. But how does this relate to
fructose and glucose? Well, for one, you
have [snorts] the sword gene in your
cells just like the mice do. But more
poignantly, fructose when it enters your
cells is converted to a molecule called
sorbital. That conversion is performed
by the sword protein called sorbital
dehydrogenase, but we're going to stick
to sword for ease of understanding. Now
during that conversion process from
fructose to sorbital sword uses a
molecule called NADH.
Like a handyman uses a hammer to hit a
nail, sword uses NADH as its hammer.
[snorts] And it's the use of NADH
converting into NAD that leads to more
aggressive cancer. So in total colarctal
cancer cells have a sword protein in
them that when exposed to fructose and
glucose generates more NAD that leads to
downstream activation of promigration
pro- invasion behavior of cancer cells.
Now I did briefly mention NAD and I
didn't elaborate further because there's
a bunch more that gets pretty technical
like the impact that NAD has on a
pathway called the malinate pathway.
how, oddly enough, statins can play a
role and more. So, if you're an uber
nerd like me and want the unabbridged
version of this video, check out the
Physionic Insiders. You'll also get
weekly articles, all these perks right
over here, plus access to my insider
community. Links in the description if
you're interested. Okay, all this is
well and good, but where's the human
evidence? Does this translate? Now, what
we've been over is in mice and in cells.
And it's usually well before this point
in the video where people will comment a
great zinger like, "I'll worry when I'm
a mouse." Or, "Mice aren't humans." And
that's when I read the comments and I'm
just blown away by this revelation. It's
staggering because throughout my masters
and my PhD, I was never taught that. I
was I'm actually the dumbest person on
earth. Or alternatively, or in addition,
it's also possible that I reference back
to corroborating human data whenever I
possibly can, especially when we discuss
mechanistic data in animals. But those
individuals simply ignore or don't get
to these parts of the video. So for
emphasis, these are studies linking
sugar sweetened beverages to more cancer
in humans.
There's also studies linking fructose to
colorectal cancer as well. Now,
interestingly, there's a bit of variance
on if sugarsw sweetened beverages like
soda are linked to cancer. The trend is
either neutral or harmful link though.
So, as a final exasperated emphasis,
yes, the mechanisms are described here
in animal research, but the mechanisms
are also plausible in humans. And there
are several studies linking sugary
drinks like soda pop to cancer in
humans. To be honest, I don't expect too
much push back on this one simply
because of the first question I asked
you at the beginning. Uh we almost all
agree that soda isn't a health benefit.
Now, if I were to replace the word soda
with red meat or walnuts, I'd already be
booting up my Cyberdine systems T800 to
protect me. Such is the reality of
unwavering bias. Okay, so what's the
skinny? We now have a mechanism of
action by which fructose paired with
glucose like heavily found in soda makes
colurectal cancer cells more aggressive.
It's through the sword enzyme converting
fructose to sorbital leading to high NAD
levels within the cells that changes the
cancer cells to be more aggressive. We
also know that there are some links also
shown in human studies even when
controlling for diet quality, body
weight, energy intake and more. So this
is not limited evidence to just animals.
the mechanistic research there is some
signal in humans too. So based on what
we know right now I think a conservative
but justified conclusion would be to
avoid soda if you suff suffer from
colurectal cancer. In fact most sugar
sweetened beverages a slightly less
substantiated but another possibility is
avoiding soda and sugary drinks in
general regardless of your cancer
status. Now, I imagine this isn't a huge
problem for most people, and it's a
small nudge for those that do indulge
regularly. Keep in mind, a once in a
while treat isn't going to do anything
to anyone. We're talking about long-term
habits. So, okay, it's relatively simple
to avoid sugar, sweetened beverages, but
there's also nutrients that, if you
don't consume enough, also raise cancer
risk. I cover that right here. I hope
this was helpful. Thanks for tuning in.
Bye.